Michael Lee

Data & Research Professional Washington, DC

Phone: 414-550-3410;

Email: mdlee12@gmail.com

SUMMARY OF QUALIFICATIONS

3+ years applying open source libraries to analyze data and build products that drive knowledge acquisition and decision making. Whether working independently or collaboratively I'm able to contribute meaningful work through strong communication skills, critically thinking through challenging data problems, and valuing the impact of diverse audiences when creating products.

EDUCATION

Masters of Arts, Urban Education (2011-2013)

Cardinal Stritch University, Milwaukee, WI

Bachelor of Science, Psychology (2007-2011)

University of Wisconsin-Madison, Madison, WI

TECHNICAL EXPERIENCE

to scrape, clean, model, statistically test, and visualize large data sets **SQL** - Scripted and retrieved data from relational databases in education

(PowerSchool) and sports (Lahman's Baseball Database)

Python – Experience using the Python programming language **Excel** – Advanced analysis skills (pivot tables, formulas, filters, etc.)

Web Design **HTML**, **CSS** – Working knowledge and editing capabilities in website

structure and styling

D3.js - Working knowledge of implementing dynamic visualizations

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

RESEARCH ASSOCIATE

American Institutes for Research (July 2015 - Present)

- Co-authored the <u>EdSurvey</u> R package for analysis of survey data including NAEP statistical methods, developing R functions from scratch (in addition to accompanying acceptance tests), two vignettes, and a presentation to synthesize the package's practical use for researchers
- Co-authored the <u>NAEPprimer</u> data package on CRAN
- Collaborated with designers to replicate a visualization using base R graphics tools to produce over 2000 visualizations of student and teacher level survey data to populate a client's summary reports
- Wrote R scripts to review data sets in longitudinal surveys for compliance with the required data quality objectives

FREELANCE/INDEPENDENT CONTRACTOR

The Ballengee Group (November 2014 - February 2015)

- Created a database of baseball performance and salary data exclusively using R software
- Modeled salary expectations for over 80 major and minor league baseball players across a 10 year period using machine learning techniques

www.mikelee.co (November 2014 - January 2017)

• Online portfolio of data visualizations and independent analyses; self created, implemented with Bootstrap, and hosted by Github

DATA ANALYST

<u>AmeriCorps VISTA - See Forever Foundation</u> (Nov 2013 - Nov 2014)

- Analyzed student data and literature to identify trends and answer operational questions
- Contributed to the development of a report summarizing student behavior, grades, and performance on assessments, accommodating for parents and guardians of low-literacy
- Supported data handling/validation to provide staff with student performance information